# TRAVIS JOSEPH KESSLER

University of Massachusetts Lowell One University Avenue, Lowell, MA 01854 travis.j.kessler@gmail.com, (978) 201-7710

Graduate student with more than six years of experience in academic research and open-source software development. Confident in directing teammates and students as a project manager and teaching assistant. Capable of communicating across numerous scientific, engineering, and business disciplines. Achievements include developing machine learning models to predict molecular properties with 34% more accuracy than the historical average. Skilled in applied machine learning, data mining/pipelining, statistics, and software engineering development/management.

## **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

## Software Languages

- \* Python, C, C++
- \* Javascript, HTML, CSS
- \* SQL/NoSQL
- \* Bash/Shell

### Software Tools

- \* TensorFlow, Keras
- \* PyTorch, Scikit-Learn
- \* MongoDB
- \* Git, SVN

### Software Environments

- \* Azure Web Services
- \* Amazon Web Services
- \* Windows Server 2012+
- \* Linux (Headless, GUI)

## Working Environments

- \* AGILE/SCRUM
- \* DevOps Lifecycle
- \* Kanban Organization
- \* MRPT DoJ Clearance

## **EDUCATION**

PhD Computer Engineering – GPA 3.81

University of Massachusetts Lowell
May 2023 (Expected)

## BS Computer Engineering - GPA 3.56

University of Massachusetts Lowell
May 2018

### **EXPERIENCE**

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Jan. 2019 - Present

University of Massachusetts Lowell Energy and Combustion Research Laboratory

- \* Leverages predictive models, including state-of-the-art machine learning models, to advance alternative fuel research
- \* Investigates methods for feature selection and hyper-parameter tuning, including random forest trees, principal component analysis, genetic algorithms, and artificial bee colonies
- \* Manages a team of undergraduate computer science/engineering students in tasks related to current research efforts
- \* Published research efforts in *The Proceedings of the Combustion Institute, The Journal of Open Source Software*, and the *American Society of Mechanical Engineers Internal Combustion Engine Fall Conference*
- \* Funded by the U.S. Department of Energy under award DE-EE0008479 as part of the Co-Optimization of Fuels & Engines (Co-Optima) project

## **Graduate Teaching Assistant**

Jan. 2019 - Present

University of Massachusetts Lowell Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

- \* Directs undergraduate students in a laboratory setting, supervising curriculum instruction, performing one-on-one assistance/troubleshooting, and administering/grading course material
- \* Confers with laboratory supervisor to formulate efficient methods of course material delivery and laboratory management
- \* Course repertoire includes Circuits I, Circuits II, Electronics I, and Electronics II

# **Technical Operations/DevOps Engineer**

June 2018 - Jan. 2019

Valora Technologies

- \* Used data mining techniques to extract client-specified information from legal, financial, and government documents
- \* Constructed data pipelines to usher client documents from intake to delivery of extracted information
- \* Trained newly hired DevOps engineers in data pipelining/mining workflow configuration

## **Undergraduate Research Assistant**

University of Massachusetts Lowell Energy and Combustion Research Laboratory

- \* Optimized predictive models to predict chemical reaction properties based on molecular structure (QSAR/QSPR)
- \* Implemented optimal neural network architectures to multidimensional input and output (training) data
- \* Developed open-source machine learning, feature extraction and hyper-parameter tuning software packages
- \* Published research efforts in *The Journal of Open Source Software*, Fuel, and the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Internal Combustion Engine Fall Conference

## **TECHNICAL COMMUNICATIONS**

GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/tjkessler">https://github.com/tjkessler</a>

LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/traviskessler/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/traviskessler/</a>

## **SELECTED AWARDS & HONORS**

Best Presentation, ASME ICEF 2019 Conference	Oct. 2019
1 <sup>st</sup> place, Symbotic Warehouse Robot Prototyping Competition	<i>May 2018</i>
Innovative Technology Solution, UMass Lowell DifferenceMaker 50K Idea Challenge	April 2017
1 <sup>st</sup> place, Francis College of Engineering Prototyping Competition	Dec. 2016

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- PB8. **Travis Kessler**, Thomas Schwartz, Hsi-Wu Wong, J. Hunter Mack. "Predicting the Cetane Number, Yield Sooting Index, Kinematic Viscosity, and Cloud Point for Catalytically Upgraded Pyrolysis Oil Using Artificial Neural Networks". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2020). https://doi.org/10.1115/ICEF2020-2978
- PB7. **Travis Kessler**, Peter C. St. John, Junqing Zhu, Charles S. McEnally, Lisa D. Pfefferle, J. Hunter Mack. "A comparison of computational models for predicting yield sooting index". *Proceedings of the Combustion Institute* (2020). https://doi.org/10.1016/j.proci.2020.07.009
- PB6. **Travis Kessler**, Thomas Schwartz, Hsi-Wu Wong, John Hunter Mack. "Screening Compounds for Fast Pyrolysis and Catalytic Biofuel Upgrading Using Artificial Neural Networks". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2019). https://doi.org/10.1115/ICEF2019-7170
- PB5. Sanskriti Sharma, Hernan Gelaf-Romer, **Travis Kessler**, John Hunter Mack. "ECabc: A feature tuning program focused on Artificial Neural Network hyperparameters". *Journal of Open Source Software* (2019). <a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01420">https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01420</a>
- PB4. **Travis Kessler**, Eric Sacia, Alexis Bell, John Hunter Mack. "Artificial neural network based predictions of cetane number for furanic biofuel additives". *Fuel*, 206, 171-179 (2017). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fuel.2017.06.015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fuel.2017.06.015</a>
- PB3. **Travis Kessler**, Gregory Dorian, John Hunter Mack. "Application of a Rectified Linear Unit (ReLU) Based Artificial Neural Network to Cetane Number Predictions". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2017). https://doi.org/10.1115/icef2017-3614
- PB2. **Travis Kessler**, John Hunter Mack. "ECNet: Large scale machine learning projects for fuel property prediction". *Journal of Open Source Software* (2017). <a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00401">https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.00401</a>
- PB1. **Travis Kessler**, Eric Sacia, Alexis Bell, John Hunter Mack. "Predicting the Cetane Number of Furanic Biofuel Candidates Using an Improved Artificial Neural Network Based on Molecular Structure". *ASME Internal Combustion Engine Division Fall Technical Conference* (2016). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1115/icef2016-9383">https://doi.org/10.1115/icef2016-9383</a>

## **PRESENTATIONS**

- PR3. **Travis Kessler**, Corey Hudson, Leanne Whitmore, John Hunter Mack. "Prediction of Research/Motor Octane Number and Octane Sensitivity Using Artificial Neural Networks". *Eastern States Section of the Combustion Institute Spring Technical Meeting* (2020).
- PR2. John Hunter Mack, **Travis Kessler**. "A Computational Approach to Screening Alternative Fuel Candidates". *New England Energy Research Forum* (2019).
- PR1. **Travis Kessler**, John Hunter Mack. "Predicting Biofuel Properties with an Artificial Neural Network". *UMass Lowell Student Research and Engagement Symposium* (2016).